Robert P.J. Cooney, Jr. papers on the Institute for the Study of Nonviolence M2198
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Robert P. J. Cooney, Jr. papers on the Institute for the Study of Nonviolence
1965-1987
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Cooney, Robert
M2198
10 Linear Feet (18 manuscript boxes, 1 os flat box, 1 card box)
Biographical / Historical
Robert P. J. Cooney, Jr. is an author, editor, and graphic designer. He joined the staff at the Institute for the Study of Nonviolence in Palo Alto in the mid-1970s. The Institute was founded by Joan Baez and Ira Sandperl in the mid-1960s in Carmel Valley, California. It later moved to Palo Alto and continued there until 1976.
Content Description
Materials consist of correspondence, photos, letters, papers, notes, mailing lists, printed material, books, CDs, a thumb drive, and other material from Robert Cooney's time working as a staff member at the Institute for the Study of Nonviolence. Topics include the Institute's "Power to the People" campaign, the Agape Foundation, draft resistance, and more.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchase; 2016. Accession MSS 2017-027.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials have been minimally processed but are open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use. Digital material is closed until processed.
Cooney, Robert
- The Land, Los Altos HIlls commune, 1973: thumbnails of negatives (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Black and white prints, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Thumbnails of negatives (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Negatives (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
- ISNV special, unique, background (Box 1, Folder 6)
- General: descriptions, outreach, pleas (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Letters to ISNV (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence - Jim Sullivan, workcamp participant (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Institute for the Study of Nonviolence journal, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
- Personal and political notes from 70's and 80's (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence - Carmel (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Photographs and negatives - Carmel and Palo Alto (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Institute for the Study of Nonviolence Journal, Carmel, 1966-1969 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Cassette tapes, 1973 session (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Record: The Wounded Night, Donny and Judy, The Rose Redwoods (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Joan Baez: background and articles (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Ira Sandperl (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Roy Kepler - essays (Box 2, Folder 9)
- David Harris: background and articles (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Will Kirkland - correspondence (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Randy Kehler - tax affinity and Traprock Peace Center, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Schedules, posters, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Talks, workshops, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Special events, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Alameda action and others, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- WTR, continental walk, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Actions, boycott of Bank of America, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Collection - dupe, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Pamphlets and literature, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 10-11)
- Literature lists, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Bibliographies 1970's, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Poetry, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Arab-Istraeli study kit; study kit for nonviolent action (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Study kit for nonviolent revolution, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Readings on feminism and nonviolence (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Bibliographies (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Literature, artwork (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Original layout boards: journal and Frog in the wall (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Letterhead (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Institute schedules (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Library on nonviolence (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Fundraising leads (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Institute mailing list on labels, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Articles (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Larry Casalino, former staff - articles, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- ISNV related papers 1970's (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Influential articles (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Julius Lester - articles (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Final years, 1875-1976 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Minutes and notes, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Mailing list November, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Closing minutes, letters and statements, 1975-1976 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Institute related miscellaneous groups (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Movement organizatons mailing list (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Amnesty International 1970's-1980's (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Vietnamese Buddhists early 70's and Paris delegation, Thich Nhat Hanh (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Briarpatch Cooperative Auto Shop (Box 6, Folder 6)
- HIghlander Center and Appalachia (Box 6, Folder 7)
- ISNV related - UFW (Box 6, Folder 8)
- F.O.R. and Fellowship magazine, 1960-1970 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Economics and alternatives (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Intermediate technology (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Land trusts (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Mountian West Land Trust (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Media (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Pacific Studies Center "Insight", 1970's (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Simple Living, AFSC, 1970's (Box 7, Folder 6)
- The land (Box 7, Folder 7)
- WIN magazine (Box 7, Folder 8)
- People's Union, constellation project, San Diego (Box 7, Folder 9)
- People's Union, UP Press, Air war vote (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Frog in the well (to sort) (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Frog in the well literature distributor (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Frog in the well (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Frog in the well literature lists (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Frog in the well correspondence, votes, letters (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Frog in the well papers (Box 7, Folder 16)
- Frog in the well literature (Box 7, Folder 17)
- Play - Eric Bentley, expletive deleted, WIN, June 6, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 18)
- Dupes (Frog and ISNV) (Box 8, Folder 1)
- After Frog and ISNV - straight talk (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Agape Foundation by-laws, statement of purpose, stem fund papers (Box 8, Folder 3)
- David Agape Foundation and Stem Memorial Fund (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Agape Foundation logo, art and negatives (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Agape Foundation brochure, boards and invitations (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Agape Foundation early papers and projects (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Agape Foundation 1970's (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Agape Foundation 1980's (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Agape Foundation, 1990-1991 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Agape Foundation, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Agape Foundation retreat and minutes, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Agape Foundation, 1995-2000 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Agape Foundation, 2002-2003 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Agape Foundation, 2004 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Agape Foundation annual reports (full set), 1970-2003 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Agape Foundation annual reports (second full set), 1970-2003 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Agape Foundation, 2005-2009 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Agape Foundation 40th anniversay, 2009-2010 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Power of the People opening (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Power of the People notes and leads (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Power of the People special (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Power of the People publications (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Power of the People promo (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Power of the People project files (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Power of the People endorsements - signed cards and letters (Box 10, Folder 9)
- Power of the People proposal (Box 10, Folder 10-11)
- Power of the People posters (Box 10, Folder 12)
- Power of the People notes and leads (Box 10, Folder 13)
- Power of the People fundraising (Box 10, Folder 14)
- Power of the People fundraising partners and past cards (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Power of the People concert, 1975 (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Power of the People list of contributed material and correspondence (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Power of the People response letters 1977 activists (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Power of the People research and correspondence (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Power of the People correspondence (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Power of the People primary correspondence (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Power of the People correspondence and autographs 1970's (Box 11, Folder 8)
- Helen Michalowski 1990's (Box 11, Folder 9)
- Bob Fitch - correspondence (Box 11, Folder 10)
- Dwight Macdonald - correspondence (Box 11, Folder 11)
- Barbara Deming - correspondence (Box 11, Folder 12)
- Cesar Chavez - correspondence (Box 11, Folder 13)
- S. Brian Wilson - correspondence (Box 11, Folder 14)
- Dorothy Day - correspondence (Box 11, Folder 15)
- Robert Bly - correspondence (Box 11, Folder 16)
- Marjorie Swann - CNVA (Committee for nonviolent action) (Box 11, Folder 17)
- Bob Swann - correspondence (Box 11, Folder 18)
- Dan Spelce, Santa Cruz activist - correspondence (Box 11, Folder 19)
- Brad Lyttle - correspondence (Box 11, Folder 20)
- Ann Davidon - correspondence (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Larry Gara (historian) - correspondence (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Jim Forest - correspondence (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Igal Roodenko - correspondence (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Jim Peck - correspondence (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Marty Jezer, Power of the People co-author - correspondence (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Henry Bass - correspondence (Box 12, Folder 7)
- Henry Geiger, Manas magazine - correspondence (Box 12, Folder 8)
- John Howard Griffin - correspondence (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Brad Lyttle - correspondence and critique (Box 12, Folder 10)
- Power of the People contacts - card files, 1975-1977 (Box 12, Folder 11)
- Information about photos and photographers (Box 12, Folder 12)
- Photo sources and permissions (Box 12, Folder 13)
- Power of the People reviews (Box 12, Folder 14-15)
- Research and photo responses (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Power of the People research, Swathmore College Peace Collection and others (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Photo research and captions (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Power of the People text, layout, and mockups (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Power of the People foreword (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Power of the People revisions (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Power of the People old text (Box 13, Folder 7)
- Power of the People update notes (Box 13, Folder 8)
- Power of the People cover reprint (Box 13, Folder 9)
- Power of the People covers and reviews (Box 13, Folder 10)
- Power of the People layout boards (Box 13, Folder 11)
- Power of the People financial records (Box 13, Folder 12)
- Power of the People check record and receipts, 1978-1995 (Box 13, Folder 13)
- Power of the People finances (Box 13, Folder 14)
- Power of the People evaluation, Helen (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Power of the People review (Box 14, Folder 2-4)
- Peace Press promotion (Box 14, Folder 5)
- Peace Press sales and royalties (Box 14, Folder 6)
- New Society Publishers reprint sales and promotion 1980's - 1990's (Box 14, Folder 7)
- Peace Press (Box 14, Folder 8)
- New Society Publishers (Box 14, Folder 9)
- New Society Press correspondence and promotion (Box 15, Folder 1)
- Power of the People 1998 survey for reprint, Don Will (Box 15, Folder 2)
- Projects and courses resulting from Power of the People (Box 15, Folder 3-4)
- Action Archives master (Box 15, Folder 5)
- Action Archives, 1990-1997 (Box 15, Folder 6)
- Chief Seattle's speech (Box 15, Folder 7)
- Power of the People first printing, 1977 (Box 15, Folder 8)
- Power of the People, book, 4 editions (Box 16)
- My draft cards, selective service correspondence, order to report, 1972- (Box 17, Folder 1)
- Correspondence - Ken Christopherson, S. F. courts employee, responce to 1972 letter (Box 17, Folder 2)
- Trial notes and documents (Box 17, Folder 3)
- Trial opening statement, testimony, closing, 1972 (Box 17, Folder 4)
- Drft trial letters of support (Box 17, Folder 5)
- My probabation, 1972-1976 (Box 17, Folder 6)
- Article on my trial, Christopher Jones, 1972 (Box 17, Folder 7)
- Conscientious objection, draft information, notes (Box 17, Folder 8)
- Draft resistance (Box 17, Folder 9)
- Draft resistance articles and papers (Box 17, Folder 10)
- Anti draft originals (Box 17, Folder 11)
- Draft resistance publications (Box 17, Folder 12)
- Draft resistance Together magazine (Box 17, Folder 13)
- Draft resistance Plain Wrapper magazine (Box 17, Folder 14)
- Amnesty - reference (Box 17, Folder 15)
- Military resisters (Box 17, Folder 16)
- Tony Williams, CO, SCU friend, Air Force, 1974 (Box 17, Folder 17)
- Paul coopersmith, Ms. of Coll VN and draft memoirs, June 2008 (Box 17, Folder 18)
- Oversize materials, Amnesty International, People's Union (Half-box 18, Folder 1)
- Scrapbook - draft resistance (Half-box 18)
- Large scrapbooks with posters, event promotions and other (Oversize-box 19)
- Judgment of not guilty for refusal to report for induction (Oversize-box 19)
- The Power of the People desk seal stamp; ink stamp (Card-box 20)